

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Porto, Portugal

🛮 (+351) 933 235 253 | 🗷 goncalojmarantes@gmail.com | 🌴 goncalomarantes.com | 🖸 marantesss | 🛅 goncalomarantes | 💆 @marantesss

Summary.

Software Engineer with more than 2 years of experience in web development working at small and medium-sized enterprises, holding Master's degree in Computer Science from the University of Porto. Working mostly with web technologies. Advocate of functional programming. Passionate about open-source, software architecture, containerization, CI/CD, software development methodologies, project management, database technologies and web development.

Experience

Freelance Porto, Portugal

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Jul. 2024 - Now

Sep. 2022 - Aug. 2023

- Developed a Tax Calculator web application for Remote Crew using NuxtJS and Tailwind
- · Building Portico, a web application for portuguese real estate investors using BlitzJS, Prisma and DaisyUI
- Keynote speaker at Portugal.vue #2 meetup

Intuitivo Porto, Portugal

SOFTWARE ENGINEER Aug. 2023 - Jul. 2024

- Used React and JSS to develop to the Intuitivo web platform, alongisde ExpressJS and PostgreSQL for API development
- Developed a native desktop version of the App with anti-cheat features using ElectronJS
- Designed and implemented a performance test suite using Locust to stress test the platform for Portugal's national exams with around 200k concurrent users
- Implemented an in-memory database solution for fast data access using Redis
- · Designed, developed, tested and distributed Intuitivo's UI component library using Storybook and GitHub Registry

Infraspeak Porto, Portugal

FRONTEND DEVELOPER

• Used VueJS with Typescript and SCSS to contribute to Infraspeak's web client

- Tinkered with PHP, Laravel and PHPUnit to contribute to Infraspeak's web API
- Used Git and Gitlab as version control systems and Jira as issue tracker and planner applications
- Designed, developed, tested and open-sourced a tool to batch migrate the Infraspeak client codebase from the deprecated Vue Class-based syntax to the Options API Syntax to aid in Vue 3 migration
- Keynote speaker at Portugal.vue #1 meetup

INESC TECPorto, Portugal

RESEARCH ASSITANT Nov. 2021 - Aug. 2022

- Developed my master's dissertation which includes a requirements engineering and design framework for circular economy ecosystems
- Took part in the H2020 European innovation project CircThread
- Published a conference paper entitled *The Design of Digital Platform Ecosystem Supporting Circular Economy* in the Collaborative Networks in Digitalization and Society 5.0 2023 Conference
- Interviewed European industrial organizations related with home appliances and energy systems life cycle to elicit organizational and technological requirements
- Created a tool to test ecosystem dynamics and informational dependencies between multiple actors of the product life cycle, which was validated by the project's stakeholder

ZeroZero Vila Nova de Gaia, Portugal

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER INTERN

Jun. 2021 - Sep. 2021

- Developed Project: Orwell, a web service to aid in the identification and categorization of website visitors. Extracts information from web requests, such as IP address, location, page visits, etc.
- · Designed the web application UI using Figma and Affinity Design. Built the entire page layout, components and interactions
- Developed the web interface using React, Bulma and SCSS; external and internal APIs with NodeJS, ExpressJS and KnexJS; database using PostgreSQL and PL/pgSQL; cache using Redis and server configuration with Traefik
- Developed server unit tests with Jest and Supertest
- · Containerized the whole service with Docker and Docker Compose, compatible with different environments

Projects

Vue Class Decorators to Options API Transpiler

DEVELOPER 2023

- CLI tool to batch migrate Vue Single File Components using a class-based syntax with <u>vue-property-decorators</u> package, to Options API syntax
- Wrote a blog post about the technical implementation and architectural decisions behind this tool

Glass Base

Developer 2021

• Developed a web dashboard and REST API to visualize data from the Portuguese government public contract platform. This application stores, serves and presents data in a more user friendly way, with metrics, charts and table

• Designed the dashboard with Figma. Developed the dashboard with NuxtJS and TailwindCSS, server development was done in NodeJS, ExpressJS and KnexJS, relational database was developed in PostgreSQL

IEEE University of Porto Student Branch

Porto, Portugal

CORE MEMBER & VICE-CHAIRMAN ON 2019

Nov. 2017 - Dec.2022

- Helped organize events (RetroJam 2019, REC 2020) and workshops (C++, Git)
- Contributed to the development of the <u>student branch's website</u>
- Designed multiple branding materials

Education

University of Porto Porto, Portugal

BACHELOR'S & MASTER'S DEGREE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2022

Master's Dissertation: A framework to support the deployment of circular economy ecosystems